KEYAN ZHAI

keyanzhai3@gmail.com <a> LinkedIn <a> Github <a> Website

My research interests lie at the intersection of CV, CG and Robotics, with a focus on the perception, modeling, and understanding of the 3D world. I am particularly excited about topics such as 3D/4D reconstruction, neural rendering, sensor fusion, visual odometry, etc. My ultimate aim is to digitize humans, objects and events in the physical world and explore their applications in industries like AR/VR, autonomous driving and Robotics.

EDUCATION

University of Pennsylvania

Sep 2021 - May 2023

M.S.E. in Robotics, School of Engineering and Applied Science, GPA: 3.81/4

ShanghaiTech University

Sep 2017 - Jul 2021

B. Eng. in Computer Science and Technology, School of Information Science and Technology

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages Frameworks Tools Python, C, C++, Java, Rust, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, TypeScript, PHP, SQL, Matlab NumPy, Pandas, PyTorch, scikit-learn, Matplotlib, OpenCV, OpenGL, Qt, Django, Laravel Git, Jenkins, Linux, Shell, CMake, GDB, Valgrind, Docker, AWS, ROS, GoogleTest, Postman

WORK EXPERIENCE

Apple Inc. - Technology Development Group

Software Engineer / CVML Intern - AR/VR Algorithm Infrastructure

May 2022 - Aug 2022 Sunnyvale, California

- · Contributed to a large-scale library codebase (2m+ lines) including computer vision, computer graphics, and deep learning algorithms used by AR/VR algorithm researchers with C, C++, and CMake
- \cdot Optimized multiple **applications** and **unit tests** for **App Clip Codes** [Link], achieving a **60%** speed improvement and removal of dependency on testing resource files, saving **100%** disk space
- · Created and automated a comprehensive **test pipeline** for App Clip Codes, encompassing multiple phases including **image rendering** and **processing**, resulting in a **50**% reduction in manual testing steps
- · Strengthened the video processing application by enabling visualization and restructuring the concurrent dataflow of multi-track video replay pipeline, facilitating issue identification for future debugging and feature development
- · Streamlined the software development cycle by refactoring library **API**s to a **production-level** with uniformed standards, ensuring best code practices and enabling efficient validation of code quality by the Quality Assurance team

Vijay Kumar Lab - GRASP Lab, University of Pennsylvania

Jan 2022 - May 2022 Philadelphia, Pennsylvania

 $Software\ Engineer\ -\ Simulation\ Infrastructure$

- · Configured full-stack simulations of large-scale multi-robot systems with more than 60 robots using Unity and ROS; developed simulation software infrastructures in Python and C++/CMake with multiple Docker containers
- · Streamlined the development workflow of cutting-edge **robotic control and planning algorithms** by restructuring them to a common interface, facilitating simplified use of the simulator for researchers across various universities

Living Machines Laboratory, Shanghai Tech University $Undergraduate\ Researcher$

Jul 2020 - Jan 2021 Shanghai, China

- · Built a legged robot [Link] equipped with IMU and strain gauge on Arduino using Solidworks and 3D printing
- \cdot Designed and implemented an **optimization algorithm** based on **Bayesian Optimization** with **Python** and applied the algorithm to the control system of the legged robot, increasing weight support by 5.54% compared to baseline
- · Presented publication [Link] as the first author at 16th International Conference on Intelligent Autonomous Systems

Shanghai Center for Brain Science and Brain-Inspired Technology Software Engineer Intern - Cognitive AI Group

Jul 2019 - Apr 2020 Shanghai, China

- · Developed an online IQ test **web application** [Link] that allows IQ test for both human and machine with Python, Django and SQLite for the first Machine Automated IQ Test Challenge (MAIQ) at IJCAI-2020 [Link]
- · Curated test **dataset** with **700+** IQ test problems including verbal comprehension, diagram reasoning and sequence reasoning; automated **dynamic generation of image dataset** with hierarchical representation of test images

RESEARCH PUBLICATION

<u>K. Zhai</u>, C. Li, and A. Rosendo, "Scaffolded Learning of In-place Trotting Gait for a Quadruped Robot with Bayesian Optimization," 16-th International Conference on Intelligent Autonomous Systems. [<u>Link</u>]

COMPUTER VISION PROJECTS

3D Scene Reconstruction from 2D viewpoints

Python/NumPy/Computer Vision

· Implemented two-view stereo and plane-sweep multi-view stereo algorithm that utilizes 5 different views to convert multiple 2D viewpoints into a **3D reconstruction** of the scene

Augmented Reality App with AprilTags

Python/NumPy/Computer Vision

· Implemented an **AR** application that shows several virtual object models in a given video with AprilTags by solving **PnP** with coplanar assumption and solving **P3P** with the **Procrustes** problem

Face Swapping in Two Videos [Link]

Python/NumPy/OpenCV

· Built a pipeline that can **detect and swap faces** seamlessly in two videos, including **feature detection** and **extraction**, **optical flow** to track faces, **image morphing**, and **Poisson blending** to make the face swapping natural

Automated Fall Risk Assessment with 3D Human Pose Estimation [Link] [Demo] Python/OpenCV

· Developed an application based on 3D Human Pose Estimation to automatically test the risk of falling for the elderly; improved joint positional accuracy with optical flow and **sensor fusion** using Unscented Kalman Filter with IMU data

MACHINE LEARNING / DEEP LEARNING PROJECTS

COVID Classification with CNN [Link]

Python/PyTorch/NumPy/Pandas

· Created a dataset of 2,500 chest X-ray images for classification between COVID and normal lungs; trained a CNN model with pretrained resnet18 backbone, reaching test accuracy of 93%

Perceiving Music Quality with various ML models [Link]

Python/PyTorch/AWS

· Created a new training dataset of 1950 music segments and applied different types of audio degradation on them; trained supervised learning models (SVM and CNN) on the created dataset to predict the audio quality and evaluated the performance quantitatively compared with existing methods

COMPUTER GRAPHICS PROJECTS

Mini Minecraft [Link]

C++/OpenGL/Qt/OOP/Computer Graphics

- · Created an **interactive 3D** world exploration and alteration Minecraft-style program including a **controllable Player** class with **simple physics** that includes player control, velocity, acceleration, position change, and collision checking
- · Implemented **procedural generation** of terrain and cave systems using **noise functions** such as **Perlin** and **FBM**, enabling efficient terrain rendering, chunking and distance-based loading with **multi-threading** techniques
- · Expanded upon the existing lambert shader to allow for UV texture mapping with provided textures

Micro Maya Mesh Editor

C++/OpenGL/Qt/OOP/Computer Graphics

· Developed a mesh editor application in C++ including the half-edge mesh data structure and visualization with **OpenGL** that supports Catmull-Clark subdivision, loading and rendering OBJ files, and binding meshes to skeletons

3D Rasterizer

C++/OpenGL/Qt/OOP/Computer Graphics

 \cdot Created a **rasterizer** for both 2D and 3D scenes in **C++** and programmed **OpenGL**'s graphics pipeline including vertex and fragment **shaders** to apply different coloration effects to the surfaces of **3D models**

ROBOTICS PROJECTS

PANDA Arm Pick-and-Place

Python/NumPy/ROS

· Implemented Inverse Kinematics based on iterative optimization with gradient descent and planning algorithms like Astar and RRT for the 7-DoF Franka Emika PANDA robot arm, enabling the robot to pick, place, and stack both static and dynamic blocks fully autonomously

Point-Cloud Based Stair Climbing of MIT Mini Cheetah [Link]

C++/Python

· Collected 3d **point cloud** data of stairs using **LiDAR** and built traversability map models; modified the **gait control algorithms** based on the map models to improve the performance of stair climbing for MIT Mini Cheetah

Autonomous Elevator Robot [Link]

C++/ROS

• Enabled a mobile robot with a manipulator to take elevators autonomously by detecting and pressing buttons; applied **AMCL** for localization, **OCR-RCNN** for button detection, and **MoveIt!** for motion planning of the manipulator

COMPUTER SYSTEMS PROJECTS

PennOS, a UNIX-Like Operating System

C/Linux/Operating System

- · Developed a UNIX-like operating system including a priority scheduler, FAT file system, and user shell
- · Contributed to development of the **kernel** which supports **process creation**, **process scheduling** with **priorities**, **signaling**, and integrated a **shell** that supports **job control**, **redirections**, and a functional set of **built-in commands**

The Sniper Multi-Core Simulator

C++/Computer Architecture

• Modified the **cache subsystem** of a multi-core x86 simulator Sniper to achieve **optimal replacement policy** that can be used by any level of CPU cache; implemented a perceptron-based **dynamic branch prediction** algorithm; conducted configuration and quantitative evaluation of **MSI**, **MESI**, and **MESIF cache coherency** protocols